Inventory of the Cliff Forster papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Cliff Forster papers
1941-2008
2013C27
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes (1.8 linear feet)
Interview transcripts, memoirs, other writings, correspondence, printed matter, and photographs relating to internment of American civilians in the Japanese-occupied Philippines during World War II, the war crime trial and execution of Japanese General Masaharu Homma, and the American diplomatic service.
Forster, Cliff, 1924-2006.
Access
The collection is open for research. The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2013.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collection
Encounters: A Lifetime Spent Crossing Cultural Frontiers, Nancy Keeny Forster, Wind Shadow Press, 2009
Biographical Note
Clifton Forster (1923-2006), was a graduate of Stanford University, was a career diplomat who grew up in the Philippines as the son of an American Red Cross employee. Following the Japanese invasion of Manila in December 1941, Forster was interned as an American civilian internee, at Los Baños Internment Camp, Philippines, for five months. Through this father's Red Cross connections, Forster secured repatriation aboard the Gripsholm in 1942, and later worked for Naval Intelligence before joining the Foreign Service.
Scope and Content of Collection
Interview transcripts, memoirs, other writings, correspondence, printed matter, and photographs, relating to internment of American civilians in the Japanese-occupied Philippines during World War II, the war crime trial and execution of Japanese General Masaharu Homma, and the American diplomatic service.
Homma, Masaharu, 1887-1946.; Los Baños Internment Camp (Los Baños, Philippines); United States. Department of State.; Philippines--History--Japanese occupation, 1942-1945.; War crime trials--Japan.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners and prisons.
- Oral interview, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Miscellaneous letters and clippings, 1953-2008 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Homma sentence & execution, 1946 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Introductory material (Box-folder 1: 4)
- Chapter revisions, 1994 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Skeen interview, 1945-1949 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Imomata / Fuijko file, 1980-1988 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Homma data (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Book proposal (Box-folder 1: 9)
- Schechter correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 1: 10)
- Homma project - Correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 1: 11)
- Eariler revisions - Backups (Box-folder 1: 12)
- America in Philippines & pre-Pearl Harbor (Box-folder 1: 13)
- Bataan Campaign, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 1)
- Bataan surrender/death march, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 2)
- Corregidor surrender, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 3)
- Washington, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 2: 4)
- Liberation - Japan's surrender, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 5)
- Homma trial articles, 1946-1980 (Box-folder 2: 6)
- Swinson on Homma (Box-folder 2: 7)
- Miscellaneous interviews, meeting notes, 1976 (Box-folder 2: 8)
- Homma, 1996 (Box-folder 2: 9)
- Homma statements, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 10)
- Homma - Japanese Military Archives, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 11)
- Skeen correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 12)
- 32 years practicing "people to people diplomacy" (Box-folder 2: 13)
- Tsunoda / Tatsumi interviews, 1982-1990 (Box-folder 2: 14)
- Miscellaneous (Box-folder 3: 1)
- Screenplay draft, 1987 (Box-folder 3: 2)
- Microsoft instructions, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 3)
- Charles Forster MS, 2002-2003 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Mt. Lassen honeymoon trip, 1909 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- Red Cross Massacre, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- Internment claims, 1941-2002 (Box-folder 3: 7)
- US High Commissioner Report, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 3: 8)
- WGBH - Carlson / Jean Production, 1997-1998 (Box-folder 3: 9)
- Research sources, 1995 (Box-folder 3: 10)
- World War I articles, 1970-1980 (Box-folder 4: 1)
- War-related articles, 1993-1999 (Box-folder 4: 2)
- WGBH Homma project, 1987-1997 (Box-folder 4: 3)
- Sayre / Commonwealth, 1936-1941 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- Miscellaneous notes and revisions (Box-folder 4: 5)
- Preparations for invasion, 1953 (Box-folder 4: 6)
- Invasion of Luzon, 1961 (Box-folder 4: 7)
- Mactan evacuation, 1979 (Box-folder 4: 8)
- Invasion - Fall of Manila (Box-folder 4: 9)
- Manila occupation / Santo Tomas, 1995 (Box-folder 4: 10)
- Photographs, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 4: 11)
- Guardians of Empire: The US Army & the Pacific, 1902-1940 (Box-folder 4: 12)
- Trial of General Masaharu Homma by the US Military Commission, 1946 (Box-folder 5: 1)
- Research contacts, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 5: 2)
- Archives, 1986 (Box-folder 5: 3)